[
  {
    "question": "By what criterion is a genetic vector chosen?",
    "answer": "Physical properties"
  },
  {
    "question": "For which company is the Atlas robot being developed?",
    "answer": "Boston Dynamics"
  },
  {
    "question": "For which industries is the potential of 3D printing particularly great?",
    "answer": "Medicine"
  },
  {
    "question": "How are recombinant proteins produced?",
    "answer": "Using DNA technologies"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can AR be applied in medicine?",
    "answer": "Surgery"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do quantum computers implement parallel computing?",
    "answer": "Superposition"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does AR assist doctors during surgeries?",
    "answer": "Clarity"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does AR help manufacturing?",
    "answer": "Instructions"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does AR improve logistics?",
    "answer": "Route optimization"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is AR useful in medicine?",
    "answer": "3D visualization of surgeries"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is augmented reality used in the automotive industry?",
    "answer": "Navigation"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is the distance to stars measured?",
    "answer": "Parallax"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is the value of cryptocurrency determined?",
    "answer": "Market demand"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many bytes are in the SHA-256 hash function?",
    "answer": "32"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many layers of services are there in the cloud?",
    "answer": "Three"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many levels of autonomous driving correspond to full control?",
    "answer": "5"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many qubits in superposition can a quantum register represent?",
    "answer": "2^n"
  },
  {
    "question": "How to prevent data leakage?",
    "answer": "Disk encryption"
  },
  {
    "question": "How to reduce mining difficulty?",
    "answer": "Reducing hash rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "How will augmented reality change the use of tourist maps?",
    "answer": "Adding interactivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year was Dolly the sheep cloned?",
    "answer": "1996"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year was the first autonomous car introduced?",
    "answer": "2009"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year were fullerenes discovered?",
    "answer": "1985"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year were the properties of graphene discovered?",
    "answer": "2004"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which education sector has AR firmly established itself?",
    "answer": "Medicine"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which field is AR used for staff training?",
    "answer": "Industry"
  },
  {
    "question": "Modern method of creating nanostructures?",
    "answer": "Lithography"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name of the creator of Android?",
    "answer": "Andy Rubin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name one type of quantum algorithm.",
    "answer": "Shor's Algorithm"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name one type of virtualization.",
    "answer": "Full virtualization"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the method of reducing data volume.",
    "answer": "Compression"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the type of bioenergy resource:",
    "answer": "Biogas"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the limitations of using cloud systems?",
    "answer": "Network dependency"
  },
  {
    "question": "Quantum cryptography protects against?",
    "answer": "Algorithm hacking"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main problem of quantum computing:",
    "answer": "Noise and errors"
  },
  {
    "question": "The technique used for studying nanostructures?",
    "answer": "Atomic force microscope"
  },
  {
    "question": "To which area of AI does a system belong that can compose new musical pieces based on studying existing music?",
    "answer": "Art AI"
  },
  {
    "question": "What AI model is used for text translation?",
    "answer": "Seq2Seq model"
  },
  {
    "question": "What algorithms are used for object recognition?",
    "answer": "Neural networks"
  },
  {
    "question": "What allows remote management of servers?",
    "answer": "SSH"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are CDNs used for?",
    "answer": "Access speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are buildings with minimal energy needs called?",
    "answer": "Passive"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are complex calculations for protection called?",
    "answer": "Cryptography"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are eco-funds?",
    "answer": "Green investments"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are gene drives?",
    "answer": "Modified alleles"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are microservices used for?",
    "answer": "Modular architecture"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are robots afraid of?",
    "answer": "Overload"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are servomotors used for?",
    "answer": "Precise positioning"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are specialists who test systems for security called?",
    "answer": "Pentesters"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the advantages of cloud computing?",
    "answer": "Scalability"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the microorganisms called that decompose petroleum products?",
    "answer": "Biodegraders"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the types of MITM attacks?",
    "answer": "Man-in-the-Middle"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are viral vectors used for?",
    "answer": "Gene transfer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What aspect is important for the realism of visual effects in virtual reality?",
    "answer": "High resolution"
  },
  {
    "question": "What aspect of blockchain makes it secure?",
    "answer": "Cryptography"
  },
  {
    "question": "What backs cryptocurrency?",
    "answer": "Algorithms"
  },
  {
    "question": "What can qubits differ in?",
    "answer": "States"
  },
  {
    "question": "What can transgenic plants be?",
    "answer": "Resistant to pests"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cells are used for treating diseases?",
    "answer": "Stem cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cells are used in gene therapy?",
    "answer": "Somatic cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characterizes the degree of entanglement of qubits?",
    "answer": "Entropy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What component is necessary for the operation of a pneumatic system?",
    "answer": "Compressor"
  },
  {
    "question": "What compression algorithm is used in the ZIP format?",
    "answer": "Deflate"
  },
  {
    "question": "What consensus is used in the Polkadot network?",
    "answer": "Nominated Proof of Stake"
  },
  {
    "question": "What control system is used for satellite orientation in space?",
    "answer": "Gyroscopic"
  },
  {
    "question": "What controls access to systems?",
    "answer": "Authentication"
  },
  {
    "question": "What data is most commonly processed by autonomous vehicles?",
    "answer": "Road signs and markings"
  },
  {
    "question": "What determines the phenotype?",
    "answer": "Genotype and environment"
  },
  {
    "question": "What device can measure distance?",
    "answer": "Laser rangefinder"
  },
  {
    "question": "What device helps reduce electricity consumption?",
    "answer": "Energy monitor"
  },
  {
    "question": "What device is used to measure plasma density in space?",
    "answer": "Plasma detector"
  },
  {
    "question": "What device is used to measure the magnetic field in space?",
    "answer": "Magnetometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What device measures cosmic radiation?",
    "answer": "Radiation sensor"
  },
  {
    "question": "What devices are used for manipulating atoms?",
    "answer": "Scanning probe microscope"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do bioreactors do?",
    "answer": "Cultivate cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do space elevators do?",
    "answer": "Transport cargo"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do vulnerability scanners do?",
    "answer": "Find vulnerabilities"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does 'tokenization' mean?",
    "answer": "Creating tokens"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does CRISPR do?",
    "answer": "edits genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does FDM stand for?",
    "answer": "Fused Deposition Modeling"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does NLP stand for?",
    "answer": "Natural Language Processing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does SIEM do?",
    "answer": "Collects events"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does a consensus algorithm mean?",
    "answer": "General agreement"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does a gravitational lens do?",
    "answer": "Distorts light"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does a quantum algorithm use for encryption?",
    "answer": "Randomness"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does an IDS do?",
    "answer": "Detects intrusions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does an encoder do?",
    "answer": "Encodes data"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does autonomous driving control?",
    "answer": "All processes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does blockchain technology allow to create?",
    "answer": "Digital assets"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does malware do?",
    "answer": "Harms the system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does nanochemistry study?",
    "answer": "Substances at the nanoscale"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does nanophysics study?",
    "answer": "Physical properties of nanoparticles"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does reinforcement learning do?",
    "answer": "Automatic decision making"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the Imitation Learning method do?",
    "answer": "Imitates behavior"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the MES system control?",
    "answer": "Production process"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the PCR method do?",
    "answer": "copying DNA"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the abbreviation FDM stand for in 3D printing?",
    "answer": "Fused Deposition Modeling"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the abbreviation MFA stand for?",
    "answer": "Multi-Factor Authentication"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the abbreviation RFID stand for?",
    "answer": "Radio Frequency Identification"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term 'cloud security' imply?",
    "answer": "Data protection"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term 'code injection' mean?",
    "answer": "Code insertion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term 'electronic intelligence' mean?",
    "answer": "Electronic espionage"
  },
  {
    "question": "What effect is used to obtain images in an atomic force microscope?",
    "answer": "Tunneling effect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What ensures uninterrupted communication of the car with the outside world?",
    "answer": "Modem"
  },
  {
    "question": "What feature of IoT devices is critically important?",
    "answer": "Security"
  },
  {
    "question": "What function does a genetic vector perform?",
    "answer": "Transfers genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What function is needed to prevent material leakage when the print head moves?",
    "answer": "Retraction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What helps manage multi-zone architectures?",
    "answer": "Terraform"
  },
  {
    "question": "What helps reduce energy consumption in IoT?",
    "answer": "energy-saving modules"
  },
  {
    "question": "What helps to reduce energy consumption?",
    "answer": "Smart lighting"
  },
  {
    "question": "What helps to reduce water consumption?",
    "answer": "Drip irrigation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What instrument is used to detect gravitational waves?",
    "answer": "LIGO"
  },
  {
    "question": "What instruments are used to analyze the atmospheres of planets?",
    "answer": "Spectrometers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is AR (augmented reality)?",
    "answer": "The combination of the virtual and real world"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is BFT?",
    "answer": "Byzantine Fault Tolerance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Big Data?",
    "answer": "Large volumes of data"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is CVE?",
    "answer": "Common Vulnerabilities"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is DDoS protection?",
    "answer": "Protection against denial of service"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is DeFi in blockchain?",
    "answer": "Decentralized finance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is ERC-20?",
    "answer": "Token standard"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Google Fuchsia?",
    "answer": "Operating system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Grover's algorithm used for?",
    "answer": "Search"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is IP68?",
    "answer": "Degree of protection against water and dust"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is IPv6?",
    "answer": "Internet Protocol"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Level 5 autonomous driving?",
    "answer": "Full autonomy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is NLP used for?",
    "answer": "Text processing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Proof of Stake?",
    "answer": "proof of stake"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is REST?",
    "answer": "Architectural style"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is ROM?",
    "answer": "Read-Only Memory"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is RPA?",
    "answer": "Robotic Process Automation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Shor's algorithm?",
    "answer": "Factoring numbers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is TWRP?",
    "answer": "Recovery shell"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Terraform used for?",
    "answer": "Infrastructure management"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Terraform?",
    "answer": "Infrastructure as Code"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a CIP system in industry?",
    "answer": "Cleaning in Place"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a DAO?",
    "answer": "Decentralized Autonomous Organization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a GAN?",
    "answer": "Generative Adversarial Network"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a Load Balancer?",
    "answer": "Load Balancer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a Trojan program?",
    "answer": "Disguising as legitimate software"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a biomarker?",
    "answer": "Protein"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a compiler?",
    "answer": "A program that translates code"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a fork in blockchain?",
    "answer": "Network branching"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a framework?",
    "answer": "A set of tools for software development"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a fullerene?",
    "answer": "A form of carbon"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a genetic vector?",
    "answer": "DNA carrier"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a geostationary orbit?",
    "answer": "35,786 kilometers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a hard fork?",
    "answer": "Network upgrade"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a neural network?",
    "answer": "AI algorithm"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a quantum dot made of?",
    "answer": "Semiconductor"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a qubit in a mixed state called?",
    "answer": "Mixed qubit"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a servo system?",
    "answer": "Automatic control system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a virtual network?",
    "answer": "Cloud network"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an RDBMS?",
    "answer": "Relational Database Management System"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an oracle in blockchain?",
    "answer": "Data provider"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is backpropagation?",
    "answer": "Training algorithm"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is bioenergy?",
    "answer": "Energy from biomass"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is considered a cyber attack?",
    "answer": "DDoS"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is decoherence?",
    "answer": "Loss of coherence"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is energy efficiency?",
    "answer": "Maximum productivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is enhanced by VR?",
    "answer": "Immersion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is gene therapy?",
    "answer": "Therapy with genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is graphene?",
    "answer": "A single-atom carbon layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is important for the reliable operation of IoT?",
    "answer": "Cybersecurity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is important for the security of IoT devices?",
    "answer": "Encryption"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is integrated into blockchain to enhance transaction anonymity?",
    "answer": "Tor"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is lidar used for?",
    "answer": "Scanning the environment"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is made from biopolymers?",
    "answer": "Eco-plastics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by 'cloud security'?",
    "answer": "Protection against threats"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is nuclear fusion?",
    "answer": "The joining of atoms"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is obtained as a result of bacterial transformation by the method of conjugation?",
    "answer": "Recombinants"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is one of the issues with using cloud technologies?",
    "answer": "Security"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is quantum decoherence used for?",
    "answer": "Stabilization of systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is quantum entanglement?",
    "answer": "Connection of qubits"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is recombinant DNA?",
    "answer": "Modified DNA"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is responsible for data analysis in the IoT ecosystem?",
    "answer": "Analytics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is retraction in the context of 3D printing?",
    "answer": "Reverse feeding of filament"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is sharding?",
    "answer": "Data partitioning"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the SVM method?",
    "answer": "Classification method"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the ability of a machine to make decisions called?",
    "answer": "Artificial Intelligence"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approach called when multiple cloud providers are used?",
    "answer": "Multicloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the difficulty level of a multi-cloud terminal?",
    "answer": "High"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the file format for software applications on Android smartphones called?",
    "answer": "APK"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the first step in security planning?",
    "answer": "Risk analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the foundation of artificial intelligence in robotics?",
    "answer": "Machine learning"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the function of SIEM?",
    "answer": "Event analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the function of a hash function?",
    "answer": "Creating a fingerprint"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the goal of display speed in augmented reality (AR)?",
    "answer": "Real-time display"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the goal of gene therapy?",
    "answer": "Restoration of gene functions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the goal of self-learning AI systems?",
    "answer": "Improving performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main advantage of a heated bed?",
    "answer": "Prevention of warping"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main advantage of nuclear energy?",
    "answer": "High productivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main barrier in the development of quantum technologies?",
    "answer": "Entropy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main challenge of quantum computing?",
    "answer": "Decoherence"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main factor that causes mutations?",
    "answer": "Changes in DNA"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main issue that can occur during 3D printing?",
    "answer": "Warping"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main principle of nanophotonics?",
    "answer": "Quantum effects"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main tool used for editing DNA?",
    "answer": "CRISPR-Cas9"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main value of IoT data?",
    "answer": "information"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the measurement of height using satellites called?",
    "answer": "Altimetry"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the mechanism for reaching consensus called?",
    "answer": "Algorithm"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the method called by which robots interact with their environment?",
    "answer": "Sensing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the method of artificially combining genetic material from different sources called?",
    "answer": "Genetic recombination"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the method of moving robots along a predetermined path called?",
    "answer": "Path planning"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of a robot controlled remotely by a human?",
    "answer": "Ion engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of a robot that can change its shape?",
    "answer": "Morphobot"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of learning using labeled data?",
    "answer": "Supervised learning"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the AI method used in recommendation systems?",
    "answer": "Collaborative filtering"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the Android version that supports 'Internet of Things' devices?",
    "answer": "Android Things"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the CNC machine control system?",
    "answer": "NC system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the VR device prototype created in 1968?",
    "answer": "Sword of Damocles"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the VR headset from Valve?",
    "answer": "Index"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the algorithm used for object recognition?",
    "answer": "YOLO"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the attack where an attacker tries to control more than 50% of the network?",
    "answer": "51% Attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the blockchain gambling platform?",
    "answer": "FunFair"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the building's engineering equipment management system?",
    "answer": "BMS"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the classification method using trees?",
    "answer": "Decision trees"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the company that creates high-precision maps for autonomous vehicles?",
    "answer": "HERE Technologies"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the computer vision technology used in smartphones?",
    "answer": "Computer vision"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the consensus algorithm in the Ethereum network after the update to version 2.0?",
    "answer": "Proof of Stake"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the emergency shutdown system for equipment?",
    "answer": "ESD System"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the fast charging system by Oppo?",
    "answer": "VOOC"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the first quantum network?",
    "answer": "Quantum Internet"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the generative model that represents some data in terms of others, such as images in the style of text?",
    "answer": "VAE"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the input-output controller in smartphones?",
    "answer": "IO-Controller"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the large-scale project to send humans to Mars?",
    "answer": "Mars One"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the last block in a blockchain?",
    "answer": "Head block"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the microscope used to study atoms?",
    "answer": "Atomic force"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the most powerful American rocket engine?",
    "answer": "RS-25"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the person who first proposed the concept of blockchain?",
    "answer": "Satoshi Nakamoto"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the popular algorithm for factoring numbers on a quantum computer?",
    "answer": "Shor's Algorithm"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the probabilistic inference technique?",
    "answer": "Bayesian inference"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the quantum algorithm for searching a database?",
    "answer": "Grover's Algorithm"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the robot competition?",
    "answer": "RoboCup"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the sensor that detects infrared radiation?",
    "answer": "Pyrometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the server virtualization technology?",
    "answer": "Hyper-V"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the space probe for studying the Sun?",
    "answer": "Parker Solar Probe"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the space telescope for ultraviolet observations?",
    "answer": "GALEX"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the sustainable farming technique?",
    "answer": "Organic farming"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the system for control and management of technological processes?",
    "answer": "DCS"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the technology that converts high molecular weight compounds into hydrocarbons?",
    "answer": "Cracking"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the technology that increases memory through compression?",
    "answer": "zRAM"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the telescope for ultraviolet observations?",
    "answer": "GALEX"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the newest data transmission format in mobile networks?",
    "answer": "5G"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the phenomenon called when a user feels a sense of presence in a virtual environment?",
    "answer": "Presence"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the phenomenon called where a user feels presence in a virtual environment?",
    "answer": "Immersion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the primary application of AlphaFold?",
    "answer": "predicting protein structures"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the primary application of nanomaterials?",
    "answer": "Optimization of properties"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the primary function of IoT devices in industry?",
    "answer": "Monitoring"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the primary use of AI in medicine?",
    "answer": "Disease diagnosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process called where a solid object is created from powder using heat?",
    "answer": "Sintering"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of DNA doubling called?",
    "answer": "Replication"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of a robot interacting with objects called?",
    "answer": "Manipulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of adjusting weights in a neural network called?",
    "answer": "Backpropagation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of analyzing network traffic called?",
    "answer": "Network monitoring"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of assembling and configuring a robot called?",
    "answer": "Integration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of collecting data using a radio telescope called?",
    "answer": "Radio astronomy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of composting called?",
    "answer": "Aerobic decomposition"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of converting an analog signal into a digital one called?",
    "answer": "Sampling"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of converting nuclear fuel into energy called?",
    "answer": "Nuclear fission"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of creating thin films called?",
    "answer": "Nanocoating"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of exploring a planet's surface using robotic instruments called?",
    "answer": "Geological exploration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of gene transfer called?",
    "answer": "Gene transformation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of information gathering by robots called?",
    "answer": "Sensing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of obtaining energy from atomic nuclei called?",
    "answer": "Nuclear energy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of production optimization called?",
    "answer": "Kaizen"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of protecting data called?",
    "answer": "Data protection"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of studying the properties of materials at the nanometer level called?",
    "answer": "Nanodiagnostics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of the destruction of a quantum state called?",
    "answer": "Decoherence"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of using other planets to launch spacecraft into orbit called?",
    "answer": "Gravity assist"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the production of medicines from living cells called?",
    "answer": "Biopharmaceuticals"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the purpose of an IDS?",
    "answer": "Threat detection"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the purpose of cloud security?",
    "answer": "Data protection"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the purpose of the 'Chandra' mission?",
    "answer": "Study of X-rays"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the role of the restriction enzyme?",
    "answer": "Cuts DNA"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the science called that studies atomic and molecular layer deposition?",
    "answer": "Atomic Layer Epitaxy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the science of applying layers of atomic thickness called?",
    "answer": "Nanocoatings"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the software for programming controllers called?",
    "answer": "PLC software"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the technical document of a cryptocurrency called?",
    "answer": "Whitepaper"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the technique called for cloning at the molecular level?",
    "answer": "PCR"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the technique called that allows the conversion of light energy into electricity at the nanoscale?",
    "answer": "Photoelectric effect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the technology called that allows a smartphone to function as a computer?",
    "answer": "DeX"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the technology called that assesses road conditions in real-time?",
    "answer": "Telemetry"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the technology called that divides a blockchain into segments?",
    "answer": "Sharding"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the technology called that routes voice calls over the internet?",
    "answer": "VoIP"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term for a non-personalized cyber attack on large groups of people?",
    "answer": "Cyberterrorism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term for exploiting vulnerabilities in software?",
    "answer": "Exploiting"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term for the disturbance of a quantum state due to external factors?",
    "answer": "Decoherence"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term for the time interval during which the image on a VR screen is updated?",
    "answer": "Refresh rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is used for manipulating nanoparticles?",
    "answer": "Nanomanipulators"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is used for training neural networks?",
    "answer": "Backpropagation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is used for transaction verification?",
    "answer": "Nodes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is used to cool quantum processors?",
    "answer": "Liquid helium"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is used to ensure the stability of a robot?",
    "answer": "Gyroscopes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is used to increase the efficiency of solar panels?",
    "answer": "Trackers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is used to optimize neural networks?",
    "answer": "Gradient descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is virtual memory?",
    "answer": "Simulation of RAM"
  },
  {
    "question": "What issue can occur during 3D printing?",
    "answer": "Nozzle clogging"
  },
  {
    "question": "What joins DNA from different sources?",
    "answer": "Ligases"
  },
  {
    "question": "What limits the current development of quantum computers?",
    "answer": "Decoherence"
  },
  {
    "question": "What makes a building energy-efficient?",
    "answer": "Insulating materials"
  },
  {
    "question": "What makes reinforcement learning methods special?",
    "answer": "Use of rewards"
  },
  {
    "question": "What makes validation decentralized?",
    "answer": "All participants"
  },
  {
    "question": "What material destroys the ozone layer?",
    "answer": "Freon"
  },
  {
    "question": "What material is often used for sensors?",
    "answer": "Graphene"
  },
  {
    "question": "What material is often used in tissue bioprinting?",
    "answer": "Bioplastics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What material is used for medical implants in 3D printing?",
    "answer": "Titanium"
  },
  {
    "question": "What material is used for supercapacitors?",
    "answer": "Graphene"
  },
  {
    "question": "What material is used to create high-performance processors?",
    "answer": "Silicon"
  },
  {
    "question": "What measure enhances security?",
    "answer": "Access control"
  },
  {
    "question": "What mechanism prevents double spending?",
    "answer": "Consensus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method allows adding a new block to the blockchain?",
    "answer": "Proof of Work"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method can be used to introduce genes into a cell?",
    "answer": "Electroporation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is often used for applying thin layers in the nanometer range?",
    "answer": "ALD (Atomic Layer Deposition)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used for gene sequencing?",
    "answer": "DNA sequencing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used for genome sequencing?",
    "answer": "Sanger sequencing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used for growing cells in three-dimensional structures?",
    "answer": "3D cell culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used for manufacturing nanoscale transistors?",
    "answer": "Photolithography"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used for protein separation?",
    "answer": "Chromatography"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used to create nanocomposites?",
    "answer": "thermoplastic forming"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used to create objects in a virtual environment?",
    "answer": "CAD"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used to determine the sequence of amino acids?",
    "answer": "Sequencing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used to introduce genes into cells outside the chromosome?",
    "answer": "Transfection"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used to lengthen telomeres?",
    "answer": "Enzymatic intervention"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used to optimize weights in a neural network?",
    "answer": "Backpropagation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used to verify a user's identity using multiple factors?",
    "answer": "Multi-factor authentication"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method of biodiversity restoration is used in ecology?",
    "answer": "Renaturalization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What mission did Voyager 1 accomplish?",
    "answer": "Exploration of deep space"
  },
  {
    "question": "What popular technology is used for IoT devices?",
    "answer": "Zigbee"
  },
  {
    "question": "What principle is used to protect information in quantum cryptography?",
    "answer": "Entanglement"
  },
  {
    "question": "What problem can arise from poor quality filament?",
    "answer": "Nozzle clogging"
  },
  {
    "question": "What problem is solved by the Proof of Work (PoW) algorithm?",
    "answer": "Double spending"
  },
  {
    "question": "What procedure is used to create thin surface films?",
    "answer": "Molecular deposition"
  },
  {
    "question": "What procedures help reduce carbon dioxide (CO2) emissions?",
    "answer": "Carbon sequestration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process cleans the generated energy from CO2?",
    "answer": "Carbon capture"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is critical for creating new cryptocurrency tokens?",
    "answer": "Mining"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is used for cloning?",
    "answer": "Somatic cloning"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is used for purifying water in reservoirs?",
    "answer": "Biofiltration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is used in fuel cells to generate electricity?",
    "answer": "Electrochemical reaction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is used to create clones of entire organisms?",
    "answer": "Cloning"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is used to increase the performance of mobile devices?",
    "answer": "Overclocking"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is used to produce biogas?",
    "answer": "Methanogenesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is used to produce ethanol from sugar-containing materials?",
    "answer": "Fermentation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process must be completed before printing a 3D model?",
    "answer": "Slicing the model"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process powers fuel cells?",
    "answer": "Chemical reaction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process produces electricity?",
    "answer": "Generation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process reduces the carbon footprint?",
    "answer": "Carbon sequestration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What programming language is used in ARKit?",
    "answer": "Swift"
  },
  {
    "question": "What property of graphene makes it unique?",
    "answer": "High conductivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What property of nanomaterials is important for solar panels?",
    "answer": "Conductivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What provides continuous network monitoring?",
    "answer": "Threat detection systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "What regulates the rotational speed of an electric motor?",
    "answer": "Frequency converter"
  },
  {
    "question": "What resolution is suitable for a high-quality VR experience?",
    "answer": "4K"
  },
  {
    "question": "What robots are used for space exploration?",
    "answer": "Rovers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What security standard is used to protect data in the cloud?",
    "answer": "SSL/TLS"
  },
  {
    "question": "What skill does augmented reality train in manufacturing?",
    "answer": "accuracy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What software assists in forecasting for autonomous vehicles?",
    "answer": "Predictive analytics system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What software is used for scanning network traffic?",
    "answer": "Sniffers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What solution is used for automating cloud infrastructure management?",
    "answer": "Terraform"
  },
  {
    "question": "What specialization is most important for IoT development?",
    "answer": "Electronics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What state can eliminate errors in quantum computing?",
    "answer": "Quantum correction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What structure is important for nanoelectronics?",
    "answer": "Nanocrystals"
  },
  {
    "question": "What substance is used in PCR?",
    "answer": "DNA"
  },
  {
    "question": "What system helps a robot determine its location?",
    "answer": "Navigation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What system helps reduce the carbon footprint of a home?",
    "answer": "Home solar system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What system is used for printing complex metal parts?",
    "answer": "DMLS"
  },
  {
    "question": "What system supports life on space stations?",
    "answer": "Life support system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technique allows for editing DNA?",
    "answer": "CRISPR"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technique is used for gene therapy?",
    "answer": "Viral vectors"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technique is used for intercepting data?",
    "answer": "Sniffing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technique is used for monitoring the fermentation process?",
    "answer": "Biosensors"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technique is used for precise control of atoms?",
    "answer": "Atomic force microscope"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technique is used to reduce the expression of specific genes?",
    "answer": "RNA interference"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technique uses viruses for gene delivery?",
    "answer": "Gene therapy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technologies help reduce energy consumption in a smart home?",
    "answer": "LEDs"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology allows a robot to recognize human speech?",
    "answer": "Speech recognition"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology allows a robot to see?",
    "answer": "Computer vision"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology allows multiple robots to work together?",
    "answer": "Swarm"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology allows the accumulation of energy from solar panels?",
    "answer": "Batteries"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology allows the restoration of lost body functions?",
    "answer": "Regenerative therapy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology converts heat into electricity?",
    "answer": "Thermoelectric"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology converts wave energy into electricity?",
    "answer": "Wave power stations"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology enables wireless power transfer?",
    "answer": "Induction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology helps reduce the energy consumption of IoT devices?",
    "answer": "LPWAN"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used for autonomous vehicles?",
    "answer": "Machine vision"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used for communication between vehicles on the road?",
    "answer": "V2V"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used for extracting oil from reservoirs?",
    "answer": "Hydraulic fracturing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used for harnessing solar energy?",
    "answer": "Photovoltaics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used for position tracking?",
    "answer": "SLAM"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used for tracking in augmented reality?",
    "answer": "SLAM"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used in MJF for printing?",
    "answer": "Powder"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used to create artificial organs?",
    "answer": "Bioprinting"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used to create detailed maps in autonomous vehicles?",
    "answer": "HD Mapping"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used to create thrust in space?",
    "answer": "Ion engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used to improve the energy efficiency of buildings?",
    "answer": "Passive house"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used to launch small satellites from a large satellite?",
    "answer": "Cubesat"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology is used to stabilize satellite orbits?",
    "answer": "Reaction wheels"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology provides the power of a quantum computer?",
    "answer": "Quantum parallelism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term describes the system for automating the technological process at a factory?",
    "answer": "APCS"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term is used to describe microbes that produce electricity?",
    "answer": "Electrogens"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term refers to the complete absence of delays in virtual reality (VR)?",
    "answer": "Zero Latency"
  },
  {
    "question": "What test does NASA use to check equipment resistance to vibrations?",
    "answer": "Vibration test"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of adhesion is used for smoothing?",
    "answer": "Cyclography"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of blockchain does IBM Hyperledger belong to?",
    "answer": "Private blockchain"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of control includes automatic adjustment of parameters?",
    "answer": "Regular control"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of data does cloud encryption protect?",
    "answer": "Confidential data"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of data is most commonly exchanged by IoT devices?",
    "answer": "Telemetry"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of data is most commonly transmitted among IoT devices?",
    "answer": "Sensor data"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of energy is obtained from biomass?",
    "answer": "Bioenergy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of energy is obtained from organic waste and agricultural products?",
    "answer": "Bioenergy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of energy is released during nuclear fission?",
    "answer": "Atomic"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of energy is used for heating homes with heat pumps?",
    "answer": "Geothermal energy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of fuel is often used in modern satellites?",
    "answer": "Hydrazine"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of modification is used to study gene function?",
    "answer": "Gene knockout"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of motor is most commonly used in industry?",
    "answer": "Induction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of printer is used for printing food products?",
    "answer": "Food printer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of robot can perform complex tasks in space?",
    "answer": "Multi-axis robot"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of robots are used to explore the surface of Mars?",
    "answer": "Rovers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What types of robots are commonly used in manufacturing?",
    "answer": "Manipulators"
  },
  {
    "question": "What types of robots are used in logistics?",
    "answer": "Warehouse robots"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the TALEN technology created for?",
    "answer": "Edit genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the first commercial VR headset?",
    "answer": "Sega VR"
  },
  {
    "question": "When was the first genetic modification of a human performed?",
    "answer": "2018"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where are biopolymers used?",
    "answer": "In medicine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where are gold nanoparticles used?",
    "answer": "In medicine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the largest solar power plant located?",
    "answer": "India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which algorithm is often used for big data analysis?",
    "answer": "RGBoost"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which algorithm is used to maintain a stable state of a system?",
    "answer": "PID controller"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which algorithm speeds up database search on a quantum computer?",
    "answer": "Grover"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which area of AI is involved in creating games?",
    "answer": "Reinforcement Learning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cells are used in genetic engineering?",
    "answer": "Somatic cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which companies collaborate in the field of VR content?",
    "answer": "Google and Sony"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which company created the Kubernetes project?",
    "answer": "Google"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which company did Rony Abovitz found for developing augmented reality?",
    "answer": "Magic Leap"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which company first introduced the concept of augmented reality in 2000?",
    "answer": "Boeing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which company partnered with Lyft to test self-driving cars?",
    "answer": "Aptiv"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which company produces self-driving trucks?",
    "answer": "Uber"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which company released the first camera phone?",
    "answer": "Sharp"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which company was the first to introduce a VR headset to the general public?",
    "answer": "Meta"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which company was the first to launch a smartphone with a curved screen?",
    "answer": "Samsung"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component converts an input signal into an output?",
    "answer": "Controller"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component is important for high-quality sound in virtual reality?",
    "answer": "3D audio"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component is responsible for changing voltage?",
    "answer": "Transformer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component is responsible for processing audio signals on a smartphone?",
    "answer": "DAC"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component is responsible for processing images?",
    "answer": "Graphics Processing Unit"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component is used for smart lighting?",
    "answer": "LEDs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component models the functioning of the human brain?",
    "answer": "Neural network"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component of a 3D printer is responsible for moving the print head along the Z-axis?",
    "answer": "Lead screw"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country is leading in the development of lunar missions?",
    "answer": "USA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country leads in solar power production?",
    "answer": "China"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which data is protected cryptographically?",
    "answer": "Encrypted"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which databases are best suited for VR applications?",
    "answer": "Object-oriented systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which device studies the cosmic microwave background radiation?",
    "answer": "WMAP"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which electron is characterized by high mobility in graphene?",
    "answer": "Dirac"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which element helps in night vision?",
    "answer": "Infrared"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which element is needed for nuclear reactors?",
    "answer": "Uranium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which element is often used to create qubits in quantum computers?",
    "answer": "Superconductors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which element is used in hydrogen fuel cells?",
    "answer": "Platinum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which element is used in spacecraft fuel?",
    "answer": "Helium-3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which element is used to create most modern qubits?",
    "answer": "Silicon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which element of the autonomous driving system is responsible for analyzing road situations?",
    "answer": "Artificial Intelligence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which element of the basic IoT architecture is responsible for data collection and initial processing?",
    "answer": "gateway"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which energy source requires the least amount of water?",
    "answer": "Wind energy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which engine uses ion technology?",
    "answer": "Ion engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which equation preserves quantum states over time?",
    "answer": "Schrdinger's equation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which farming method reduces the use of chemicals?",
    "answer": "Organic farming"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which field studies the application of nanoparticles in medicine?",
    "answer": "Nanobiomedicine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which field studies the interaction of nanomaterials with water?",
    "answer": "Nanohydrodynamics"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which game is considered a pioneer in the use of VR technology?",
    "answer": "Half-Life: Alyx"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which gas is used in fuel cells?",
    "answer": "Hydrogen"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which gene is used in gene therapy to fight cancer?",
    "answer": "p53 gene"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which green technology improves water quality?",
    "answer": "Wastewater treatment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which heating method is more environmentally friendly?",
    "answer": "Geothermal"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which important experiment confirmed the existence of superposition and entanglement?",
    "answer": "Double-slit experiment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which instrument has atomic precision?",
    "answer": "Scanning tunneling microscope"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which instrument is used to study cosmic microwave background radiation?",
    "answer": "WMAP"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which layer in the IoT architecture is responsible for data processing?",
    "answer": "Analytical layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which material is known for its high strength and electrical conductivity?",
    "answer": "Carbon nanotubes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which material is suitable for bioprinting tissues?",
    "answer": "Hydrogel"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which method adds a new block?",
    "answer": "Addition"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which method allows for the determination of the exact sequence of nucleotides in a DNA molecule?",
    "answer": "Sequencing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which method allows robots to act collectively?",
    "answer": "Swarm intelligence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which method allows the use of metal for 3D printing?",
    "answer": "Selective Laser Sintering"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which method increases the conductivity of nanomaterials?",
    "answer": "Doping"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which method is safe for storing information?",
    "answer": "Secure hard drive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which method reduces overfitting?",
    "answer": "Regularization"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microalgae are used for biomass production?",
    "answer": "Chlorella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microorganisms are used for the biological treatment of wastewater?",
    "answer": "Bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microorganisms are used for the synthesis of vitamin B12?",
    "answer": "Propionibacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microscope allows you to see atoms?",
    "answer": "Scanning tunneling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which molecule is involved in protecting plants from pathogens?",
    "answer": "Salicylic acid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which molecule is used for gene labeling?",
    "answer": "GFP"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which nanomaterials can change color when exposed to light?",
    "answer": "Fullerenes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which network is best suited for a smart city?",
    "answer": "LPWAN"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following improves the conductivity of materials?",
    "answer": "Silver nanostructures"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which organism is often used for genetic manipulation?",
    "answer": "Escherichia coli"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which organization assigns international safety standards?",
    "answer": "ISO"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which parameter determines the internal structure of the model?",
    "answer": "Infill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which parameter of a 3D printer determines the amount of material extruded over a certain period of time?",
    "answer": "Flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which plant is often used for biofuel production?",
    "answer": "Corn"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which plant uses the Earth's heat?",
    "answer": "Geothermal plant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which plants are used for phytoremediation technology?",
    "answer": "Sunflower"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which plants are used for studying genetics?",
    "answer": "Arabidopsis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which printer setting affects the internal structure of the printed item?",
    "answer": "Infill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which printers use metal powders for printing?",
    "answer": "SLM"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which process improves the properties of materials in nanotechnology?",
    "answer": "Defect control"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which processor is suitable for IoT devices?",
    "answer": "ARM"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which protein is used for binding DNA?",
    "answer": "Histone"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which proteins are involved in the body's immune response?",
    "answer": "Antibodies"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which proteins are used for DNA editing?",
    "answer": "Nucleases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which protocol is used for energy-efficient IoT device connectivity?",
    "answer": "Zigbee"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which protocol is used for real-time data transmission?",
    "answer": "RTP"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which protocol protects emails?",
    "answer": "PGP"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which robot is known for its involvement in cooking and can prepare dishes?",
    "answer": "Moley"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which rocket launched the James Webb Telescope into orbit?",
    "answer": "Ariane 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which rocket uses methane engines?",
    "answer": "Starship"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which satellite monitors the global sea level?",
    "answer": "Jason-3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which satellite provides monitoring of Earth's climate?",
    "answer": "Aqua"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which science studies the interaction of nanoparticles with cells?",
    "answer": "Nanobiology"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which scientist proposed a quantum algorithm?",
    "answer": "Deutsch"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which security technique involves increasing complexity?",
    "answer": "Encryption"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sensor is used to measure angular velocity?",
    "answer": "Gyroscope"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sensor is useful for measuring vibration?",
    "answer": "Gyroscopic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which service increases resources on demand?",
    "answer": "Auto Scaling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which smartphone is considered the first Android device?",
    "answer": "HTC Dream"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sugar substitute is produced biotechnologically?",
    "answer": "Stevia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which system helps autonomous vehicles navigate in low visibility conditions?",
    "answer": "Infrared cameras"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which system provides a car's connection to the outside world?",
    "answer": "Telematics"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which system uses HD maps for navigation?",
    "answer": "Autonomous driving systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology anchors a 3D model to the real world?",
    "answer": "SLAM"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology controls nanoparticles?",
    "answer": "Atomic microscope"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology facilitates motion tracking in virtual reality?",
    "answer": "Markers"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology helps reduce electricity consumption in the home?",
    "answer": "Smart home"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology helps reduce energy consumption in homes?",
    "answer": "Smart windows"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology helps to avoid collisions?",
    "answer": "ADAS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology incorporates machine learning algorithms into manufacturing?",
    "answer": "Artificial Intelligence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology is most effective for air purification on an industrial scale?",
    "answer": "Electrostatic filter"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology is often used for storing data in a temporary table?",
    "answer": "Redis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology is often used for virtualization?",
    "answer": "VMware"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology is used to create isolated containers?",
    "answer": "Docker"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology reduces the emission of harmful gases into the atmosphere?",
    "answer": "Carbon capture"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technology securely connects IoT devices?",
    "answer": "VPN"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which test assesses a machine's ability to mimic human thinking?",
    "answer": "Turing Test"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which tool checks for vulnerabilities?",
    "answer": "Nmap"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which vehicles can use AR for navigation guidance?",
    "answer": "Cars"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which virtual reality (VR) game is based on shooting mechanics?",
    "answer": "Superhot VR"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which virus is most commonly used for gene therapy?",
    "answer": "Adenovirus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which waste processing method reduces the amount of waste?",
    "answer": "Recycling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who can validate transactions in a public blockchain?",
    "answer": "Anyone"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who coined the term 'robotics'?",
    "answer": "Isaac Asimov"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who created the first industrial robot?",
    "answer": "George Devol"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who developed one of the first approaches to deep learning?",
    "answer": "Geoffrey Hinton"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who developed the game Beat Saber?",
    "answer": "Beat Games"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who developed the laws of robotics?",
    "answer": "Isaac Asimov"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who founded the company Huawei?",
    "answer": "Ren Zhengfei"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who introduces genetic material into microorganisms?",
    "answer": "Synthetic biologist"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who invented the steam engine?",
    "answer": "James Watt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is considered a pioneer in the field of nanotechnology?",
    "answer": "Eric Drexler"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the founder of Honor?",
    "answer": "Zhao Ming"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the founder of the concept of IoT?",
    "answer": "Kevin Ashton"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the primary user of AR in construction?",
    "answer": "Designers"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who proposed the idea of a quantum computer?",
    "answer": "Richard Feynman"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who proposed the idea of manipulating atoms?",
    "answer": "Eric Drexler"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who proposed the wave model of quantum mechanics?",
    "answer": "Schrdinger"
  }
]